I'll wait until you're over there
Okay, great test test test testing audio for the stream. Am I coming in clear? It's a Willy Wonka reference. Is it working?
Yay All right. Good evening, everybody
Now call to order this special meeting of
Lancaster City County Council Finance Committee for October 21st 2025 Just a little housekeeping for ourselves in the beginning before I turn it over to councillor Arroyo
oh mr. Harris would you please call the roll of members yes madam president mr. man here mr. Roya here please miss Craig here misty is mr. Hirsch here and president Pekka here tonight's meeting our department budget presentations it's our first budget hearing of the year I will
turn it over to council Arroyo Thank You council president before I turn it over
to director campbell to kick us off i wanted to allow the public um some information um after each presentation this evening we will welcome public comment uh please approach the mic and limit your comments to three minutes uh we allow we will allow for a total of 10 minutes and we ask that any additional comments or questions be submitted via the engage lancaster platform
on the wall on the wall of each side of council chambers you will find a qr code that will take you directly to engage lancaster for those watching at home it's the first listing on
the engage.cityoflancasterpa.gov website and on the video description of youtube with that
i will turn it over to director campbell to kick us off good evening good evening can you hear me all right can you hear me now great let's see if i can work this properly
perfect all right so before i jump into the administrative service services details this
evening i just wanted to provide a quick reminder and overview of the budget process
so this is the organizational structure of the city for 2026 this is something that i think you all have probably seen before there's five separate departments of the city between tonight and November 18th you'll hear reports from all of these departments as well as the mayor's office and a short report on this on the clerk and elected officials as well
so tonight you will hear from the department of administrative services which I will share
the director Delves will then share about the department of community planning and economic development and then our two chiefs of the public safety bureaus police and fire will share their updates and projections so even though police and fire are technically in one department they are both large bureaus and provide obviously unique and important public service so they'll provide separate reports this evening and here is the schedule that i presented on october 6th
at the overview presentation of the budget so just a couple of reminders on october 7th we
posted the draft budget on the website and also on the engage lancaster page The page is open for questions and comments, as Councillor Arroyo just shared, and I will answer those publicly on any of the upcoming dates that are listed here, depending on when
the questions or comments are received.
Tonight's budget hearing is bolded there, and I just reviewed that agenda, and then
November 18th will be the second budget hearing, and that will consist of all of the other areas of the organization.
So the mayor's office, elected officials, neighborhood engagement, public works, as well as the utilities or enterprise funds. November 25th, then, is the first reading of the budget ordinance, and that will, again, be time for public comment. And then I will also be available at the regular finance committee meeting on December 1st to answer any questions that come through Engage Lancaster.
And December 9th will be the second reading and vote on the budget.
All right. So jumping into administrative services, the Department of Administrative Services is divided into four bureaus and the director's office currently. So the four bureaus
are accounting and finance. Our bureau chief of accounting and finance is here tonight,
Michelle Bush, right behind me. Treasury, human resources, that bureau chief is also here tonight, andrew who is also beside michelle here um and data and technology and i don't think david is
here this evening i didn't see him um the fund development administration is uh grant oversight
and management and that falls under the director's office um our department does a lot of back office work for the city as well as providing customer service for customers and residents for utility and real estate bills through our through our treasury office for 2026 the proposed share of the general fund budget for administrative services work is nine percent uh totaling 7.1 million you can see that portion in red on the graph here and it's also bolded on the side most of these expenses are salaries however we also are now including the majority of our data end technology systems in this budget. So this is reflected here. This includes all types of
technology from our core processing systems to our physical devices to telephones and other
communication needs and anything that is related to technology. I want to briefly share some highlights from each bureau from 2025 and a few of our goals for 2026. So first in the director's office my office currently consists of myself two individuals on our grants management team and our administrative services manager who provides a lot of administrative support as well as overseeing our property liability claims process and our credit card purchasing
systems and process and i highlight that because i wanted to start by highlighting that we have started a better process for our property claims reporting in 2025 to ensure that
we're tracking trends and expenses better for our property claims a couple of other highlights we have also spent quite a bit of time this year working on increasing management reporting so actually having reports to help us make data informed decisions so you'll see this i put this as a recurring thing because you'll see this on a couple of the other bureaus as a highlight as well i'm not going to talk about all of the highlights and goals that you'll see here but just wanted to to mention a couple um for our for our for 2026 just again for the sake of time
i'm going to highlight a couple of goals but only talk about the first two that are listed here
so through much discussion over the past year with many people and departments we've decided
to move the permitting functions of the city under administrative services for 2026. Permitting is a complicated government function, so although most people think of building
permits when we say permitting, we process many different types of permits, including stormwater permits, right-of-way permits, health licenses, and many others. So these functions currently live in various bureaus and departments, and we've recognized
that this process needs to be consolidated in order to get to the improvements that we
know are much needed. We're currently also outsourcing some of our work to third-party companies, which also adds to the complications. So currently we're approaching this as setting up a separate Bureau of Permitting within the Administrative Services Department. We're still very early in this work, and therefore I didn't add a new Bureau specifically into the proposed organizational structure. I anticipate that this will require a large portion of my time and time from others who've already been very involved in this work as we work to create this new structure in 2026
but we are also anticipating two new positions with this new structure so a leader bureau chief role as well as a second permit coordinator to complement the good work that our current permit coordinator is already doing we anticipate that these roles would ultimately be covered by
increasing um permitting revenue as we would be able to to get a more coordinated system and be able to process more permits in-house and then the second goal that i'll just highlight on on here is related to our medical insurance i've alluded to our health care work um you know on october 6th and i just wanted to to mention this briefly we've been working this year to review our entire approach to health insurance and we're recognizing that we just need to start to look at how we're
working with insurance to try to contain costs in this expensive and ever increasing expense that we have as our benefit so i want to reassure everyone that this doesn't mean that we're decreasing health benefits for our employees through all of our research this year we feel like there's ways to continue to offer our great benefits while also saving on costs but this This may mean adjusting how we're working with our provider networks.
And so we're in this process currently, and this is also going to be an area of focus of my time in the next year. All right. So I'll just talk through again a couple of the highlights and goals that you see on this. You can see more goals listed than what I'm going to talk about this evening, but please review these slides at your convenience and reach out to me with any questions. So as part of the recurring theme that I mentioned earlier, in 2025, accounting has spent a lot of time working on enhancing our data analysis and monthly reporting processes. This is a work in progress, but already it's helping us to understand our data in better ways. We also implemented our first official capital budget this year, which I know I keep talking about, but it's exciting that we actually have this system in place now. And for 2026, we're focusing on updating our processes for how we manage contracts in collaboration
with our procurement manager and how we manage our fixed assets. These have both been tracked outside of our core accounting systems previously. We're now moving these systems into the core accounting system. And while these may seem like mundane projects, completing the implementation for both of these things will have a huge effect on the workload for the accounting team and the timing
of the audit which we would like to see done much earlier next year for the treasury our biggest highlight for treasury in 2025 is that we are finally able to get our auto pay up and running it went live on july 15th and since then we have received over 35 000 payments through the system and it is running well we had a small issue last week when trash bills hit the system for
the first time because those are still quarterly but the treasury staff worked hard with our software provider to get that corrected and things appear to be running smooth now and otherwise we
have heard a lot of appreciation from customers and residents for the new system for 2026 we're working on a couple of things but one of those is consult consolidating our billing cycles so we currently have 17 cycles of utilities to utility bills that we bill this means that we're running a cycle almost every working day of the month so we're trying to consolidate this down to
four which will eliminate a lot of additional work for the bureau as well as our meter shop
and it'll also help to get the number of days of each individual bill more consistent
for the bureau of human resources 2025 was definitely a rebuilding year we now have our new bureau chief in place and that's going to help us start 2026 with some renewed capacity so we're excited about that work did continue this year however despite less staff capacity we just ratified a new contract with AFSCME the non-uniformed bargaining unit
union just last week we spent some time in negotiations this year actually working through some of the language that needed updating in the contract it felt like a bit of a slog but
I'm grateful to the AFSCME leadership both local and regional for working through this with us and
and we think this work will help us to make the contract more understandable for future years.
For 2026, the HR team will be working closely with me on the health care process that I just described. We're also still working to rebuild the HR team and are proposing adding two new positions to provide some much-needed additional support
based on recommendations from a variety of outside consultants and experts. we're also looking at potentially changing our human resources software to take some of the manual burden off of the hr team um in for the for the bureau of data and technology
uh 2020 in 2025 many of the successes of other bureaus and departments were really driven by
technology that our i team it team has found and implemented implemented so big thanks to them
for all of the work that they have put in behind the scenes this year
As I have already mentioned, we have approved our first capital budget. This work was made a lot easier by the implementation of new capital budgeting software, which integrates with our core accounting system and also allows us to include a public component,
which will show each project and the progress of the project in a simple online search. We don't have that available yet, but you can see that that's one of our goals for 2026 to get that up and running. The data team's also been very involved in the regular management reporting that I've referenced, and we are also in our final stages of training to implement the first phase of CityView, which is our licensing and permitting software. So the licensing portion will go live in November, which means that all the licensing across all departments will be digital, with the goal that this process will be greatly streamlined.
and then in 2026 the permitting function in City View will roll out probably by
early summer and this is a piece that is going to help that permitting function that I was referring to earlier as well I also just wanted to briefly mention
the transition of the fiber network so the citywide fiber network currently supports all of our traffic signals and all of the Lancaster safety coalition
cameras and we're implementing a new network management tool that will help us that will help to provide visibility coordination between the parties and
direct maintenance troubleshooting so it's a switch that will eventually support additional efforts to reduce internet service costs as well all right
so the expenses for administrative services have gone up almost 10% this year and there's a few factors associated with this increase expenses in the director's office you can see have increased by 21 percent so there is
a typical cost of living increase for salaries but the only other increase in
my office is the two new positions for permitting that I mentioned earlier
otherwise all expenses have stained stayed the same with the exception of
our professional services line which actually decreased slightly now that the
home role transition work is getting to the end of completion accounting and
Finance increased by 5.8%, but beyond the typical cost of living increases, this is
a result of increased costs for our audit and cost studies that we need to do annually. Treasury actually decreased costs this year despite cost of living increases and the addition of one position. This decrease is largely because of savings in postage, which is mainly due to the auto pay and e-billing push that we've had this summer and fall. We anticipate that postage costs will continue to adjust down as we have more customers signing up for e-billing. Human resources only increased slightly this year, again despite adding two positions and the salary increases. Some of this really decrease or staying the same is the shift of current technology costs to IT, which I'll talk more on that in a minute. But we're also anticipating that we can cut some of the service costs as we're hiring more people to do the work in-house. And then data and technology saw the biggest increase in the administrative services lines this year. This is the second year of our shift to include much of our technology expenses for the entire city within this bureau so previously they were scattered throughout the organization which included the enterprise funds and in order to better track costs for technology we started to shift these costs to this bureau in the current year in 2025 and we're continuing that shift in 2026. so we may have some smaller pieces that shift in 2027 but the majority of the shift will be done with this proposed budget um some of this shift does come from the enterprise funds so you will see that those funds are paying about 35 percent more in i.t allocations in our general fund revenue if you look at that revenue line but some of these costs that are coming into
i.t this year are from the general fund and so they won't all be reflected in that enterprise on allocation in the revenue line so yeah it won't be quite apples to apples with that additionally we had some technology positions that started part way through this year in 2025
so 2026 is reflecting full staff for the full year for the first time and this also reflects pulling that current the current permit coordinator into administrative services right now housed in data and technology she her her salary has been has been spread out across the other departments but now we're pulling that into into data and technology just quickly here on staffing I've talked about all of these but we're proposing adding five new positions in administrative
services two of these are the permitting positions that I've been talking about two are in human resources that i mentioned we're also proposing adding one role in treasury this is a supervisory role and this is mainly due to some succession planning that we need to do in 2026.
we anticipate that this number will not always be at 19. we anticipate some shifting around in 2027 so we're not anticipating that to be a permanent increase but just for this year and I also just want to mention I put some asterisks in this slide we I just mentioned that we shifted the current permanent coordinator to to data and technology based on the permitting shifts in admit to administrative services so while it looks like we increased the positions by six rather than five that position was already in the 2025 budget just split into different departments and not reflected in admin services most of the department presentations that you'll see tonight and on November 18th will include department revenue admin services doesn't really generate revenue but I just wanted to point out one shift that we made at the beginning of 2025 that's resulted in some additional income so we were we were able to adjust some of our cash balances to a different investment account and it has greatly increased our investment interest it's this is still a very liquid fund so it doesn't restrict usage of the cash and it's one that's specifically for Pennsylvania
municipalities but it allows the city to earn more interest when we're not when the cash is it needed to cover expenses all right and then just briefly I did
also want to share two slides that speak to the supporting expenses portion of our budget so this portion of the budget falls under administrative services and it makes up about 15 percent of the general fund it's about 12.9 million these supporting expenses
include medical pension and debt debt expenses this category also includes our property and liability insurance packages and it includes our community involvement pieces like our support for lemsa lancaster rec the library and community communications i spoke extensively on october
6th about pension medical and debt so i won't speak more on those today medical is included
in the fringe line here so it's not specifically called out but the french line also includes other fringe benefits that are offered at the city and our property and general liability insurance
continues to increase as it is nationally so we've included the 2026 estimates for those packages here as well and then just the community involvement that includes our communication costs and so the main increase in this is a much needed upgrade to our city website i will end
there thank you director campbell i'll open up questions from the full council counselor med
thank you mr vice president and thank you director campbell for the presentation My only question is, with some of the additional staffing and the expenses increasing by roughly 10%, do we think that this will be at a level plateaued for the next couple years,
or are we going to anticipate having to add additional staff in 2027? Yeah, I don't anticipate having to add additional staff in 2027. And like I mentioned with the technology shift, I anticipate that that's going to level out as well.
Thank you, and that was my only question Thank You councillor men comes president. Thank you. Dr. Campbell. Thank you for being here and presenting for us tonight my questions around Permitting and consolidating and permitting. It's this comes up a lot when people talk to us about Frustrations with permitting process. So I'm really happy to hear that we have a plan to hopefully address that and I think that
instead of having many disparate apart departments sort of oversee that bringing it together sounds like a good idea can you talk a little bit about some of like the benefit that we're hoping to
realize for our residents what that would mean because I do think you know we're gonna look
across this budget and see different positions and I think it's important to highlight like what does that really mean when we're bringing in more people I'm looking back because I think director Delves is also gonna talk a little bit about this too but I will talk I will
say a little bit and then he can say some more yeah so the goal with this is to really try to figure out how the how to streamline the permitting process so
when somebody comes into the city and says I am doing X on my property we want to be able to get them to the point where they can actually do the thing
that they're trying to do quickly and efficiently and this is this is a way of kind of streamlining that workflow to be able to get to that point and this may
be getting a little in the weeds and it might be something that director Dallas will talk a little bit about so if that's the case just let me know and
we'll defer it to then but it is the the purpose of the new position being or is
the direction of this being a little bit more consultative for folks and just trying so I know that it's difficult to navigate um I've run across it myself too so is the purpose to be like more consultative and help people in that process that is that part of it that is part of it I um I'll say a little bit and I know the mayor wants to say something too so um that is part of it I think the other part is to also help um in some of the educational components that are needed for residents who don't normally work with the permitting system but need to come in and figure that piece out too I think that that's touched on a couple of things if
I can just add that it's also an internal accountability system to understand where the permits are how many days they are with particular staff and to ensure that those permits that the flow of permits from the time they come in to the time they are issued is meeting benchmarks in terms of number of days and so one of the things that we've heard from the public is that they don't quite understand what happens to the permit once that once it comes in and so
this would be an opportunity to provide more internal accountability and then obviously external accountability I'll also just say that from you know from
the permitting perspective we are pushing out new information about what permits are needed that continues to be a major issue but I think one of the things that I'm hoping Chris will talk about is that a couple I don't remember exactly when we brought on Kyle but one of the things that we continue to run
into is the number of the amount of work that's happening in the city that is not permitted and so as we have a part-time person that's going out and talking to folks who have started work that they should have gotten permitted for that is
also just increasing the volume of permits that's coming through so we're dealing with a couple of different we're dealing with about five different issues simultaneously related to this whether that's technology whether that's internal controls and accountability whether that is just from a customer
service perspective what's necessary as well as the increased volume and then we also have to take into account how that volume is impacting staffing and so
there's a lot that's going on in this sort of cluster of issues around permitting that we are trying to sort out and I think what I want to just make sure that everybody gets is that City View and the launch of City View related to licensing that's gonna start in November is literally just one small piece and it's probably the most straightforward piece you come in you get a license you can um you or renew your license for a rental property things like that so that's
just one part of this ongoing process thank you thank you council president counselors uh thank
you um i had two questions uh the first is just around the general goals of the additional hires
particularly in hr and data and technology um can you just speak specifically i know a consultant recommended two additional hires in hr just wondering what the specific goals of those hires and same with it and the position that was added to treasury as well that would be my first question um we didn't actually add a position to it so i'll just i'll just start with that it's just moving that position from it was it's already here it was just moving it from different
departments into the budget of i.t so that is not we have hired fully this year well we have
one vacant position now but that was because somebody left so um but we are that is a that's a full um for hr um we are looking at adding some help on the talent acquisition side um we have a
good a good amount of uh support on the on the benefits side we feel um though we are also
working on some of that piece um and then as well we're we're looking at hiring some learning and development support for our professional development and training for our staff
and i'll just on the learning and development piece um this goes way back um to an original report and i'm just doing doing this for you tim stuhldreier the management assistance partners report that was prepared for mayor gray included a recommendation for our hr department to include a learning and development um a component we tried to scale that up during my time as mayor
but did not have the dedicated resources to do that and what we find is that we we have a lot
of training that we need to be doing internal to the organization um related to hr man and management um people are complicated it turns out so this is a recommendation that is literally
two plus decades in the making and i'm strongly supporting it it was recommended in 2007 so thank you my second question I'm not sure if it should wholly go to you or to kind of a
smattering of the of the directors but I did want to like highlight the bonuses that are listed in the personnel can you just explain broadly are those is it being run through the department director or is that you overseeing it are they incentive performance based or are they distributed among the the staff of those departments like kind of across the board and who's eligible I guess yeah um so those are it's it's two different components of the AFSCME contract um so it's just specifically
for the the non-uniformed bargaining unit so it is related to merit bonuses so those are based on performance evaluations that happen in the spring of each year those are done through supervisors and then ultimately get approved by the department director as well as there was a ratification bonus included in the contract for this year so those are the two components of it thank you Thank You councillors any additional questions or comments from council just a couple questions director Campbell regarding the Bureau of permitting can you talk a little bit about what got us to the decision of
needing a bureau necessarily for that I'm curious to know because it sounds like we're still some processing and mapping out that needs to be done what made us determine that we need a bureau established that seems more like a
long-term like that's a commitment to create a bureau yeah i mean this has been uh quite a long conversation and it has developed into many different things and so we i i that's why i didn't put it into the organizational structure because i think we're still talking about it i do think that we are all feeling like we need some sort of uh coordinated effort which because administrative services kind of works with all of the departments it made the most sense to have some sort of coordinated effort within administrative services and it felt like it needed to be more than just under the director's office so that's kind of why we were thinking about it as a bureau at this point does anybody else want to say anything on that
still tbd we we this is something that that um there's been a lot of machinations about and it's probably going to continue okay thank you uh yes and appreciate the the brain trust coming together to try to solve try to solve this challenge so um and then the last question that i have is regarding uh revenues uh so with fund development and administration i know part
of the uh strategy is around sponsorships fundraising securing grants for the city i know that you know taxes don't always cover um you know the expenses that we generate so just
kind of curious about the strategy for 2026 raising funds through securing grants and what
does the opportunity look like and how do we feel that division is for that next year yeah it's a
great question um i didn't mention it but we do have about 84 million in grants under management i'll just say that now we have about 13 million that was awarded in 2025. um as we look to 2026 it's it is the the the landscape is a little bit unknown because a lot of our grants had been
coming through federal or state sources we we anticipate that the state sources will continue
but the federal sources might not be quite as you know much of an opportunity for us and so we're working one of our goals is to really try to identify new funding sources for the organization
over the next couple of years great thank you um any questions or comments from the public come on up good evening mr stu drier go ahead um a couple of comments and then a couple of questions um preface by saying um recognize that budgeting is a months-long process and listening to a 10-minute presentation and jotting a few notes is not the same as pouring over the stuff for months so with that caveat um number one um congratulations for actually drawing you know spending less on treasury three percent less that's fantastic and um you know keep up the good work and look for doing that in other
areas um i share um councilman hirsch's you know just concerns slash questions about number of positions on the one hand absolutely sounds like they're justified on the other hand positions always cost money and once positions get established can be very hard to claw them back number three with regards to the permitting and the regulations um yeah i i'm again share council's questions about that if i'm going to cped to do like a
land development plan and then i have to go somewhere else to get my permit i have to go
to department of public works and then have to go to see my permit get my permit it's certainly not clear to me how that would make things more efficient or streamlined so that would be my main question and um again uh if we're making things more streamlined ultimately they should reduce expenses and personnel and it sounds like we're increasing expenses and personnel so i'm not sure how that all adds up um would also suggest and i'm going to put on my strong hounds strong towns lancaster hat for a second here uh one way to streamline permittings by actually reducing and and eliminating regulations strong towns has what they call the six policies for a housing ready city one of them is streamline the approval process cities can implement 24 hours approvals for straightforward projects like duplex conversions backyard cottages and starters homes making
it easier and faster to get built this reduces cost encourages development and provides communities
with the homes they need without unnecessary and costly delays it also incentivizes small
developers and incremental development which helps the local economy yeah my
question then is twofold number one reducing billing cycles from 17 to 4 is that something that city residents would be seeing would that change what they're experiencing terms of their billing it initially may change because the billing
cycle the days in the billing cycle may change initially as they're adjusting it but it wouldn't necessarily change uh so that might change the days the bill comes but not the number of bills
they get correct yeah okay um reducing the number of bills you get would may be another way to reduce costs and um you made a reference to securing additional fees from permitting uh is that because you're not paying a third party or because you're actually getting more
fees from applicants it would be because we're not paying the third party great thank you very
much thank you any additional questions or comments from the public great thank you director campbell okay next i'll welcome director delves for uh the department of community planning and economic development good evening good evening council mayor sirachi we'll we'll keep it rolling
with community planning and economic development here bear with me just for a moment okay we all set yes great um i i feel like uh some of this information will will not be new for all of you
i i feel like i have uh presented uh much of this background material for you many years in a row but i'll try to move through it quickly just uh to provide additional uh context and uh backdrop for financial conversation as you all probably remember we have gone through a series of organizational development and restructuring in the department and we have settled on our current structure which is going very well we have a great management team that's made up of myself and deputy director Rebecca Geiser and And then we have four bureau chiefs, the Bureau of Planning, Betsy Logan, Bureau of Building
Codes Administration, James Nixon, Bureau of Health is Craig Walt, and last but not least, Bureau of Property Management, excuse me, Bureau of Property Maintenance and Housing Inspections led by Randy King. And as you can see here, we have a few sub offices or programs within each of those bureaus as well. As you'll see in the pie chart here, community planning and economic development makes up about 7% of the general fund budget.
This equates to approximately $5.4 million. Our budget has increased a little bit this year. We'll talk about that in a little while. On the whole, in the five to six years that I've been here, it has been relatively flat, with some exceptions.
Before we jump into the money part I wanted to talk a little bit about our highlights for 2025 and 2026 goals. I took a slightly different approach than Director Campbell. We actually have additional highlights and goals but I decided just to put a couple under each column here just to keep it as really as tight distilled as possible.
I know we have a lot to get through tonight. thing that I wanted to note here is that our community development block grant program has been going very well the spending has been on track for that program some years ago when I first got here that was one of the big issues that we had is making sure that we were meeting all of our spending requirements for CDBG we're doing a good job in on that front CDBG as as you know is used for a number of different programs and activities within the city one that we talked about the most is affordable how affordable housing both affordable housing production and affordable housing preservation you can see in this next bullet just wanted to give you a highlight related to the progress that that we've made in this space just in 2025 alone we've had 73 new affordable housing units that
were constructed they were completed and have come online and also wanted to note as we're looking back over the last three about three year period we've invested over 6.4 million dollars in
affordable housing and that will translate into really does translate into 195 additional units they're under development now. Just sticking with the community development block grant theme for a moment, you have heard some of our staff speak about this earlier this year. We do have a big milestone coming up with this particular program. We're sunsetting the five-year consolidated plan
and we're about to engage in the next five-year segment and that would be from 2026 to 2030.
there is already good work that's been happening with respect to community engagement and pulling together ideas with respect to program priorities and also how those allocations might ultimately take shape just to give you a sense of how how the consolidated plan was set up over the last five years this This pie chart represents the major priority areas for the financial allocations. You can see here in red 26 percent for maintaining quality affordable housing, 23 percent for increasing affordable housing opportunities, 20 percent for promoting neighborhood quality of life, 17 percent for expanding economic opportunities, and then ultimately 14 percent for planning activities and administration of the program as well that that pie chart represents
about 1.5 million dollars in total and uh allocated again according to those fractions
oh i should say um just in terms of timing uh you should expect a city council that will be coming back and having an in-depth presentation on cdbg in april of next year moving on to our next bureau bureau of health i think it's important to note that in 2025 we completed healthy lives healthy lancaster community health and well-being assessment this really was a first of its kind flagship project for us in the city there have been other community health assessments that have done been done but at the county or regional level never with a focus on city residents specifically really give kudos for the team for accomplishing that also wanted we've
talked a little bit about this and i think it has gotten some press but i think it's worth mentioning again that we have completed the original five-year lead hazard control high impact grant
that was a total of 9.7 million dollars over that five-year period and we were able to make 433 homes in the city led safe within low-income census tracts here in lancaster city so very very proud of that and of the team. We have noted in some other forums that we also did secure an additional Office of Healthy Homes grant recently for 7.75 million dollars that will take place over the next four years. As far as our 2026 goals, really very much connected to the Office of Healthy Homes and the lead hazard control work. We also, that same team delivers critical repair
projects as well. And this has been a very, very popular and effective program. And it seems even when we try to allocate dollars through CDBG and other avenues, it never seems like we have enough. We always have a waiting list and we're going to be buckling down again and looking
for additional opportunities, sustainable funding opportunities for critical repair coming up this year. Also wanted to note the the Bureau of Health, while
much of what we just talked about has to do with public health overall, one of the
primary business activities that the Bureau of Health does on a regular basis
is partnering with and making sure that our food businesses are in compliance with food code and that we often derive a lot of interesting stats from the team about how food businesses are doing how many have opened that kind of thing and we want to continue putting energy and effort into that realm and develop more education just to make sure that we're we're providing that that helping hand
and guidance to businesses as best we can recognizing that the culinary scene is really critical to what what we do here next up is property maintenance and housing inspections
happy to report that based on the organizational development that we've done as part of that bureau
we've gotten to a really good place in terms of our resources and our delivery of those services
we we're on track again this year to hit our performance targets so far in 2025 we've inspected
about 3 000 properties through our regular systematic uh inspection program in addition to that we also respond to complaints that we uh that we receive related to property maintenance and we responded to a total of 6 688 of those thanks to our fix it uh app that we use that application we do actually know that our average response time for those uh property maintenance complaints is about 36 hours so our turnaround has been very very fast you've probably heard us speak in the past about looking at the systematic inspections on a four-year cycle and want to make sure that we get to all rental properties within that four-year period actually we'd like to do it in even shorter that amount of time but at most we want that to be a four-year cycle and we are forecast to have accomplished 14 000 rental properties next year and based on the stats
of that time period we're seeing that our property maintenance inspectors have helped
realize a 95 percent achieving a 95 percent lead safety uh mark through their work um finally we'll
talk more about this at a later time i don't think we really need to get into a lot of details right now you may remember that we made some significant changes to the property maintenance and rental property property ordinances a couple years back and those have served us very well there are a couple of elements related to those ordinances that now need to be modified due to the home rule changes that we've made so we're going to be coming back to talk to you about those to make those
adjustments for the Bureau of Planning this has been a record year for us in terms of planning and small area planning in particular we have three that are ongoing right now one is the East End small area plan which includes the current prison site prior to the future relocation of the prison use we also are engaged in a stadium district small area plan and that's a partnership with the CRIZ staff and specifically Lancaster City Alliance and then third is the Sunnyside Nature Preserve looking at a site design for that entire nature
preserve and coordinating that with upcoming land development for the
Environmental Center and that's a partnership with partners for environmental stewardship. I think it's also worth noting here that our staff
who supports the Land Bank Authority and the Redevelopment Authority are doing a
very nice job. We know that we're going to be creating 27 housing units based upon
six property transfers that have happened recently through Raccoon Land Bank, and we also have three
that have been fully rehabilitated and now have delivered an additional 11 units that have come
online. Looking ahead to 2026, I know that we've all been anxiously awaiting updates to the zoning code that will be getting underway next year along with updates to the subdivision land development ordinance our bureau chief betsy logan recommended that we look at these concurrently i think that
was a good a good move so we'll be looking at the zoning ordinance the saldo and also our official map concurrently i did just note here that we want to adopt the east end small area plan through
city council um that that may be the case for other small area plans as well this is the one that is most directed by city staff and the idea is it would come to the planning commission first
for recommendations and then ultimately adoption by city council okay we're we're going to um get
get back to some of the permitting questions soon i think it is important that we talk
about building codes as its own entity first building code one of the core functions of building codes obviously is to issue building permits but um there's a whole set of code compliance that uh they uh that they engage in they're doing both plan review and then inspections of those properties and that's really the technical work that's happening behind the permit issuance i wanted to give you a little bit of a sense of the volume of permits that the city
is dealing with uh or processing on a regular basis just the building codes bureau alone is processing over 2 100 permits per year if you add all the other permits and licenses and approvals
that is more on the order of 3 000 permits plus so we had some questions earlier about about the resourcing for this particular need and i just wanted to note that if we take 2100 building
permits per year and then divide that by a number of weeks in the year that means that there's 40 building permits being issued each week which is an absolutely staggering pace when you stop to think about how much work that is required by staff this past year we only had two um fully trained building officials we've actually brought two more on recently but when we only had two
people on, that meant that there were 20 to 22 of these per person per week. And this isn't just issuing a permit. This is doing the plan review, doing the inspections, coordinating with all the third parties. So I think it is fair to say that we've tried to be very lean about our investments
in staff because we've needed to do that over the years. But this is an area that has, to be perfectly frank been probably underwater for a long time what one of the things
that director Campbell mentioned that we're trying to do related to the to the technology improvements one piece here that was already implemented was utilizing blue beam software to receive all building plans all commercial building plans electronically that has been going well that has helped some of our efficiency so therefore if you're passing if you have a plan set it it doesn't necessarily have to go in sequence from one reviewer to the next and people can see those comments in one place in a digital set of plans that that's really intended to
be the precursor to what we will be accomplishing with the city view software um ultimately the goal here that we're looking for i think the question came earlier like why why do we want to invest in
uh the permit function and building codes in particular i i think one answer is honestly uh the the amount of demand and and frankly complaints that we get about uh this as a city service is significant and i i really do think we need to focus on doing better here and doing better means that we're improving the quality of the plan review and the inspections and and and the speed and the accuracy of the permit issuance.
And as the mayor mentioned earlier, this is something that we should be able to measure. It's very hard to measure right now,
and part of that is because we don't have a team that is managing that function. We don't have software that's managing that function. If you think about all the parts of the permitting process, there are individual technical reviewers that are doing their piece,
there's nobody that is actually managing the permit function the mayor and i have talked about
this in the past as the the permit function is sort of the assembly line right so you do need you do need people who are managing and tools who are managing the assembly line not just the technical review of the permit permits themselves and i think that that is really the quintessential difference that we're we're looking at here um i'll come back to this briefly briefly in a little while uh after we talk about the finances okay um as you can see here we do have uh an increase in in in proposed budget uh within the department the two main areas where you're seeing changes um or the most significant changes are in the director's office at 12.7 percent increase uh and in building codes uh 26.2 percent increase on across the department this adds up to 10 10 increase overall i think it is it's worth noting here that usually we're looking at about a three percent increase just based on natural costs uh medical insurance etc if we take that three or four percent out then we're looking at uh that remaining six percent
that really relates to these program enhancements that we're talking about related to the director's office and billing codes, and I will come back to those in a little while. As Director Campbell mentioned earlier, most of the increases that we have in the general fund budget have to do with
salaries. It's not necessarily major changes to our operating line expenses. That's the same for the community planning and economic development department over a course of years we really brought down those operating lines about as far as they could go and so unfortunately there's not really any more give there as you'll see here there's one new position that's proposed in the director's office and then one additional position that's proposed in building codes as well I've been sharing our analysis about the revenue related to the community planning and economic development department the last few years and I have to give Rebecca a lot of credit who we talk about this and work on this a lot coming from a place where I've worked in the public in public policy public management for a very long time really and until like this is a compliment for Lancaster City. Until I came here, I was never as hyper-focused on the revenue side of the ledger as we have been here. And you can see here in 2026, for the first time, this is over the last
three or four years, we have been closing the gap between the costs for the department and revenue for the department. So in 2026, this is the first time that we're showing we're actually going to be bringing in more money than we're going to be spending as a department. so I feel I'm very happy about that milestone and very important to note that some of this month the revenue that's pulled in is not going directly
to CPED staff there are a whole variety of administrative support staff support across the organization so you can't look at this just through through one lens but if you're comparing the costs in your and the revenues this is
something that we're very proud of in the department. Okay so forgive me I
jumped ahead a little bit because I got going on the permit office topic. I do feel very strongly about this after observing the work and the challenges over the last few years being here. One thing that I wanted to add to the
Mayor's comments and Director Campbell's comments is that we have had a permitting project team that has been meeting regularly for for a few a few months now okay many months we've been meeting we've been meeting for many months now and it's a number of leadership within the city government who have been putting their heads together about how to how to deliver
this function better and this is really how we arrived at this concept not to say that it is a hundred percent baked but I do think that it represents the consensus ideas of those who have worked on this particular effort and the other
concept here again is that we would be hiring a bureau chief of permitting who would really be managing that function day in day out I thought Tim still
comments about the six policies I think it was for how to improve permitting
that is exactly the type of thing that a bureau chief of permitting should be focusing on day in and day out to make sure that you're getting those performance standards that you want in addition to that bureau chief of permitting there would also be one additional permit coordinator as director Campbell mentioned and I and I would I would ask that you consider the building official proposal one additional building official as part of the budget
as the broader approach to meeting this need so we've really thought about these as a package of of improvements or a package of staff additions to get the improvements that we want okay last but not least we do have one other one other position that has been proposed in the budget within the director's office. This is an economic development manager position. There's a lot that could be said here. I think I'd like to start by saying when I first arrived in Lancaster, there actually was an economic development
administrator position that was held. And that person served as essentially the first
point of contact for questions related to business that person also served as a connective tissue of sorts we have a really strong ecosystem of nonprofit organizations that focus on economic development but one of the things that has I've seen as being a challenge here is the city does not have a person who is always helping to steer and and drive on a daily basis those those nonprofits in addition to that we have a lot of work that is coming out of city planning for example related to our our corridors um our commercial corridors that have been identified in the comp plan catalytic sites for redevelopment that kind of thing that this position could be focused on delivering we We're facing a lot of economic headwinds right now, I think is fair to say, and we're seeing that manifest in a lot of different ways locally. I think it is the time to really invest. We'd cut this position to save money over a period of years, and I think we're at a
point now where it's time that we reinvest in a person who's dedicated to this. This position is envisioned as being slightly higher level than the economic development administrator that was here five years ago and would have a fair amount of independence and latitude but would be reporting to me and Rebecca within the director's office. So those are the two program enhancements the two big changes that are proposed within
CPED is the additional building code official and economic development manager. I'm happy to answer any questions about those proposals also if there are individual questions about uh the operating budget line items uh happy to do that too thank you director delves um any
questions or comments from council counselor med uh thank you mr vice president thank you director dolls for the presentation um i had a few questions first would be you know you talked about sustainable um funding streams for the critical repairs program in the upcoming years are there
any ideas of what those funding streams may be since it is a popular program um within the the upcoming years we have thought about about this quite a bit and of course we have pursued some opportunities at the state and federal level if if those indeed dry up we're going to have more difficulty but for instance we have thought about setting aside a like a portion of the fee revenues that we've
received from the data center for example for example thank you and what the enhancements made to the department other than the two positions are some of these additional expenses one-time expenses or would they be year-over-year
councillor Amman which which expenses are you thinking of just to make sure I'm answering your question correctly I mean just for instance I mean other than
the two positions that are proposed I mean with the 10% increase I know three
four percent of that is annual cost of living increases but you know in streamlining the Department of Planning or the Bureau of Planning some of those things are these going to just be one-time expenses other than the additional positions yes thank you for for clarifying I had taken down some
notes here just related to other increases that didn't have to do with those two additional positions uh we have medical insurance was up 131 000 um we had an additional 25 000 in planning professional services for the zoning update um there are other funds going into that project as well but there that 25 000 is coming out of the would be coming out of the general fund uh budget we also have an additional 31 000 for codes professional services um this is a little bit misleading because what the intent here is we would actually be paying for more residential inspections and that allows our internal staff to do more commercial jobs through doing that commercial plan review and commercial inspections that actually increases our revenue to offset some of the costs thank you my last question was about the revenues with the fee
revenues up 70 percent um i think that's great how do we continue to try to maximize that and what is the nature of some of those fees while i would like to come back every year and say that
that number keeps going up i i do uh have a feeling that we're starting to to maybe max out
some types of those revenues we um especially if we're doing more commercial
Code jobs in-house That's where most of that additional revenue is coming from and there's only so much more that we can do there
Thank you. And just lastly, I think the economic development manager would be great And I look forward to seeing that in the upcoming years and that concludes my questions. Thank you. Thank you very much My question is really just to clarify. I want to make sure I have it, right? So the position change in the director's office is that the proposed economic development manager position is that okay? I wanted to make sure that I had that correct and then
obviously if if this is
approved in the budget This is a very specialized position. So I assume there will be a period of time where it wouldn't necessarily be full
No, I wouldn't necessarily be filled and have you considered a job description for this role or is that something that you want to hold until the next administration i do actually have a draft of the job description
not not final actually have not um gone through that process with hr yet but uh we we do have something as an example of that would be helpful my only comment would be that i think it would
be wise to hold um that and allow uh next administration to have some input on that as thank you oh and council president i did want to note also that we did some analysis of the cdbg program and that position is eligible to be funded through cdbg we don't want to pre-judge that because the cdbg process is happening later but i think that's an important uh one to note because it may not have to come uh entirely from the general fund budget thank you that's good to note council craig thank you council um in the bureau of planning codes typically how long does
it take to get a permit and go through the permitting process that's a great question and a really tough question because it depends on the type of project that it is some projects have a whole set of permits and approvals that they need if it if we're just talking about
building permits uh i know that our our goal was to have that permit turned around in in about two
weeks and we're we're not hitting that standard on average um it can it's extended at times to three weeks four weeks uh and if that is for a relatively simple permit that's just not acceptable
And then you mentioned that there were two persons going through the permitting process But there was another two persons that were adding or that have already been added Great question so we have two commercial code inspectors right now and we have two residential code inspectors who
Are still in training and we've we've proposed to have one more additional building code official as part of the budget
we've tried to be very we've done a lot of analysis and we're trying to be as clear as possible about matching the staffing level with with the demand and Rebecca actually pointed out to me the other day that this is the process that we actually went through with property maintenance and housing inspections we did a lot of organizational development to get to the point where we had the right staffing and we were able to meet those performance goals of all rental properties in less than than uh four years and so we're really going we're starting that uh in earnest that that process with building codes and trying to make sure we're right sizing the staff
perfect thank you counselor thank you um just one question uh i think you might have alluded to this in uh an answer that you gave counselor med um but who is conducting the review of the zoning in saldo and because i know we had talked about it being a consultant i think at one point is that still the case and what would the progress be on that um as it stands now yeah thank you counselor um that project falls within the planning bureau under our bureau chief betsy logan we did issue an RFP and got a response to that RFP so we have just started
reviewing those proposals and our intent is to have a selection by first quarter of next year unfortunately our calendar did slide a little bit because of some
of the other zoning stuff we are dealing with right now but we it is a top priority for us thank you thank you councillor hirsch um director delves just a couple questions um regarding the healthy lives healthy lancaster initiatives i know we completed the assessment what's kind of been the outcome of that and what are next steps for that after that assessment
that's great thank you france uh asking that question i think uh sometimes this gets over overlooked a little bit this was a an incredible uh piece of work and i think um
So maybe what would be best is we could bring Craig Walt and the team to speak about that project, just to give you a few ideas here, kind of at the 40,000-foot level.
I'm just trying to come back to my notes here. Okay, so the framework that they established as the public health priorities, these are just big topics, so I apologize.
are somewhat general but sustainable communities access to services homelessness and community health public health emergency preparedness and climate responsive public health and just we actually do have some money that was allocated for the implementation of the plan i believe it's about 200 000 to select a few seed or pilot projects to get implementation underway and just a couple of these concepts really wanted to focus on ensuring that food systems are providing accessible and affordable and healthy foods and a great project that exemplifies this is the bay street garden that has been under the purview of of craig and his team i also want to promote
wellness and recreational programming for youth and families and older adults to foster that
physical and mental well-being and then last but not least this is maybe a topic
for another time I think it connects it could connect to the critical repair program the idea is that we're implementing additional home energy efficiency and climate resilience that we we would have to find the right
funding sources and set up the program to do that but I think that is like an exciting area of potential in the future okay thank you questions or comments from the public good evening is this on uh marshall miller 100th block of east fine street uh director delph thank you for the information tonight this is really great to hear um quick question for you circling back to the critical repairs program i was wondering if you could speak to the benefits of having that sustainable funding that you mentioned for the critical repairs program and what you would consider to be a minimum threshold for an annual allocation that would
make that sustainable to you? Thank you. That's a great question. This program has been absolutely
instrumental. As you may know, the critical repair program really focuses on those types of
often catastrophes that determine whether someone can stay in their house or not. It's typically a roof or an HVAC system could be like a horrible sewer lateral issue. And our Office of Healthy
Homes has, in part because we got this federal grant up front, it really built the capacity of our Office of Healthy Homes team. And they have been able to complete projects at a really impressive pace over the last year or two. So my goal is really that we don't lose that staff capacity and that they're able to continue doing projects at that pace. Your question about what
is the appropriate funding, if you don't mind, I may like to think about that a little bit, but I can say that in the past we've probably had in the realm of like $200,000 or $250,000 dollars per year going from the CDBG program, we could easily double that amount annually
and knock out those projects. Great. Thank you. That's really helpful. And then I wanted to follow up on the Bureau Chief of Permitting and kind of centralizing these processes. A complaint that I've heard repeatedly from folks who are trying to build in the city or just deal with permitting generally is the lack of visibility and transparency into the process would this bureau implement technologies that would perhaps create public-facing dashboards digital tools that would make the whole process a little bit more easy and less opaque for folks who are trying to get things
through the system yes absolutely that's that's the intent and a lot of this has not been visible
yet because it's been happening in the background but we have made some initial strides in that regard um even the basic permit finder that we just put up on the website was intended again to be a bridge towards city view and some of these other tools um i would also offer that having that that partnership or someone acting as a concierge i think is really is really imperative
uh president baquet mentioned this before related to someone who can help guide and navigate and be
a consultant i give uh credit we we've hired one permit coordinator kelly already and she's been serving that role and in some ways it's just she she can't get to everything and she's also not within a management structure yet and that's the purpose of the office i agree with you it is exciting and i thank you for your answers thanks thank you uh tim stuhlder 800 block of george street uh as before a couple of comments and then a question uh yeah as far as comments i would um
second what marshall said i've also heard concerns about um permitting and streamlining that and making it more transparent would be fantastic um on along the same lines um improving the building codes function would also be really i think important and and welcome so adding an official that sounds like a good way to to do that on the systematic inspections um i would suggest cped might want to consider a couple of things first of all we have been doing lead safety remediation there are several hundred homes that have been successfully remediated as we've heard
and if all of them have been respected all of them should at least be led safe at this point not to
say we shouldn't continue it and continue systematic inspections but for example if I have say a 75% chance of getting inspected rather than a hundred percent chance of getting inspected I'm probably still gonna be on the up-and-up because that's still a pretty good chance doing a fair
randomized inspection might be a way of being able to draw back that function a
little bit while preserving the intent and effectiveness of that program yeah and then congrats on covering your costs and then some that's also exciting from
someone who in case it's not clear is pretty focused on the city's bottom line
respectfully I would urge council not to approve the creation of an economic
development manager position as mr. Delv saluted we have multiple nonprofits in the city including Lancaster City Alliance EDC I believe there is a proposal to add a city chief of staff part of the city's chief of staff position that person could be a liaison with those nonprofits really personally don't see what a full-time person would would add to that function would also mention the Democratic candidate for mayor has some economic development
experience so that presumably would also be something he could be in on and any project that would be I think big enough for a economic development manager to take an interest in probably the mayor and the mayor's office would be taking interest in it as well so i see that position as candidly redundant and then lastly my question is
we were budgeted for 4.9 million in cped but apparently our projected expenses for this year
is 5.4 million um what was that extra expense due to and how was it offset and was any of that
offset coming from reserves can you ask that question again tim because i just want to make
sure we had the years correct i'm looking at 2025 budget um as amended i'm seeing top line figure 4.9 million 2025 projected 5.437 million and i'm looking at the budget draft pdf from the website director campbell says we're going to have to take a look at that okay thank you okay good question though thank you we just generally speaking we often uh have staffing vacancies which leads to
that change but this year uh thankfully we we do not have a big um staffing vacancy situation
so that's why i'm feeling a little perplexed in your question and i just want to check the numbers yeah thank you this is indicating spending above uh budget has passed may i approach the bench
sure i think so and while you do that tim just because i gave a talk about this today are um 95 of the systematic inspections now have led safe um uh that have been deemed lead safe so that's a really good uh rate uh for us and i would also just say that as it relates to um our ongoing we that it can be considered in the future as it relates to uh our lead inspections but i would just say that properties deteriorate over time and our continued focus on doing those lead inspections in rental properties um is a really important uh service for us to continue thank you any additional questions comments uh amos thoughts who is uh 100 block of south arch street uh i just want a question of clarification director delves uh i think you had mentioned in the kind of a one-time expense in this next year 25 000 for the zoning code update uh was that correct yes that's correct and i'm assuming that the zoning code update will
will cost a lot more than that so what is the what's the plan to be able to pay for that yes that's correct um we we did have uh additional money uh set aside through cdbg primarily and we do have a budget but we don't have proposal uh fee proposals yet i don't believe yeah i don't have more information on that now but yes you're correct the 25 000 was just supposed to be a small
portion of the overall cost and the rest would be covered by cdbg right that's that's the intent okay i just was stating that because my one of my concerns you know as a member of the planning commission we're two years out from the comprehensive plan approval haven't made much progress on the zoning code update i know that we had applied for a grant last year i think from dcd and didn't get it and i was just concerned that if we don't have enough funds in the budget like we just really have to get this done next year so that was my concern i agree with you we also do have some money in the director's office for professional services which i usually use to supplement other projects in in the other bureaus so we have a little bit of flexibility there too okay so you're confident that we have the money to do this next year we will find a way to do it next year great um and then also following up on tim's question about the economic development uh director or manager could you just say a little bit more specific about what you see that role
doing um and the implications that would have for like lancaster city alliance which has done a lot of the you know heavy lifting when it comes to economic development i think it would just be
helpful to know a little bit more you know you kind of described it as sort of liaison liaising with non-profits i was just wondering if there's more kind of meat in that job description yeah i think there's a whole host of things that this position could do and haven't haven't flesh this out entirely yet as i mentioned i do have a draft job description and
you're right this person could play a very important role in serving as that
connective tissue with the other organizations because uh there there are some questions for me about um is the city uh really steering and and driving um a lot of these initiatives in the way that we could be we have great relationships with those organizations they're doing a great job i also think there probably could be uh more um more interface that had benefits for both sides uh and then just one last follow-up question have you got an input from those organizations on that role and kind of what's the sense that you're hearing like do other do these organizations also feel like this is a gap that needs to be filled by the city i have not had a lot of
conversation with those organizations so far i can say that i work very very closely for lancaster city with lancaster city alliance and um you know we've got marshall and jeremy and i leadership levels doing a ton of work that could be happening at a staff level as well and it makes it very uh difficult to get uh sort of all the output that you could if you were fully staffed thank you great thank you and just uh a comment um regarding my day job around economic development having close relationships with a lot of nonprofits that do great work around economic development
one of the consistent feedback that i've received that the city is can do a lot more to lean into small business support and navigating the amount of resources that exist within our community and also navigating some of the departments within city hall from a small business perspective so really appreciate you uh looking into this position for for future use um also just a comment around the lead abatement and completing that grant the number of homes that uh were serviced through that grant that that's a huge deal and i just want to commend you and your team to getting
that accomplished i know it was a heavy lift to get that program up and running building trust
with the community and actually implementing um those services so kudos to you and your team to making that happen thank you i appreciate it can i just address tim's question about the projections because we found the issue so thank you for finding this for us we had merged two of the
offices together um in from the 2025 budget to the 2026 budget in the bureau of health and we were actually double counting some salaries there so we'll get that adjusted so we're not projecting to be over budget this year great i i didn't think so so appreciate you verifying um and and council royal thank you for your comments too i this this is a longer conversation that we can all have about economic development but one of the things that that we
have noted is in the building on strength plan that is really focused on a lot of traditional
development real estate development and what kind of impact that can have which is very very
important but it may not be as focused on some of these issues like business assistance economic mobility workforce development and those are all areas that i see this position could focus on yeah
and you know uh something as a counselor and former chair of the economic development committee
something i'd like to see our city do more of is really do an analysis of what types of business are needed in our community as well which i could see this position kind of filling that gap um you
know we we have a lot of non-profits that support you know entrepreneurs but what are the businesses that are needed and where are the gaps to be filled within our community so there's a huge opportunity there so thank you any additional questions or comments awesome well thank you director Delphs thank you all appreciate it with that belief chief Mendez is next on the agenda with or fire okay I have an old agenda sorry chief Hutchison with the fire bureau good evening good evening councillors and mayor Sirachi tonight we'll go over the 26 proposed budget for the fire bureau i want to thank everyone for the opportunity to present uh the good things that have happened in the bureau in the last year and uh what we're looking forward to in 26. so the bureau of fire
we are consistent uh we consist of four different divisions we have our special operations we have our fire suppression is which most people know mostly from the fire bureau they're the ones
handling the day-to-day emergencies doing the inspections for fire permitting along with our our fire marshal division which is prevention and enforcement of the fire code here in the city and our maintenance division is one of our smaller divisions along with our admin services division they are one person each and he that person maintains our equipment and our vehicles for the fire bureau our underneath myself we do have a deputy chief of operations and he is also in charge of the emergency management for the for Lancaster City which he coordinates all kinds of really a lot of internal emergency planning for the actual city buildings and employees along with the larger scale emergencies and mitigating and recovering from large-scale floods or any major
disruptions in the day-to-day operations of the city and our admin services
manager handles our training are developing our budget getting the training scheduled for our members so the 26 budget for the fire bureau is a
little over 14 million dollars which represents about 17% of the general fund
budget again we really appreciate the commitment to public safety and the support that we get from this city in in our operations so some of the highlights as of right now as of a couple days ago we responded over 2,000 emergency calls we've logged over close to 6,000 training hours on the job and off the
job maintaining an emphasis on her readiness and professionalism we did place into service a new fire suppression engine that was actually purchased in 24 took delivery at the end of 24 and until it gets all the
equipment mounted and the personnel trained it was put in service the beginning of 25 we will be transitioning to the new national emergency response information system that goes by nearest that is a federal mandate that will transform how we collect and report fire data nationwide again some of the goals
is that nearest is going to go live on January 1 and that is a mandate from the
federal government we we are in the process of revising our five-year
strategic plan the current plan does sunset here at the end of 25 and we're going to be following our risk reduction plan that we're developing right now additionally we're anticipating hiring of one firefighter we may have two other ones that will need replaced in that in 26 that's just a projection we
really can't say for sure until we have the retirement papers in hand and then can see go from there another big cost that we're going to see for 26 is a
phase 2 programming of our radio system and that's going to be a mandate through
the Lancaster County for interoperability so that's you can have more users on the county system since we do share that system with the fire emergency services
and the public works departments across the county. Our special operations division that is kind of a newer division that we're trying to trying to get more developed and get more of our
firefighters involved in and what that does it's a lot of the urban search and rescue disciplines
So you'll have a lot of trench rescues, a lot of collapse rescues, high angle, low angle, cave rescues.
It's a kind of a discipline with multiple areas that you can train in. And a lot of that training that our firefighters are receiving is through the federal government, and which is a great opportunity to develop our staff and bring back the training and train the staff locally with what they're learning throughout the nation. Some of the highlights, they did take place. If some of you all remember, there was a trench rescue in York County a few months back.
They were involved in rescuing that individual, and it was a unique situation where the trench had collapsed right against the house,
and our personnel that were working had to be inverted and dug by hand because that's how small the trench was. So it's just a lot of unique specialized skills that they're developing. We did participate in the silo rescue recovery. That was just a couple weeks ago in Upper Laycock Township. And they've really represented the city at national conferences and getting those technician-level certifications. and and right now they are in the establishing a USAR duty officer program where working with our county partners will develop on-call duty officer program that they can go out and assess situations without getting a full response from the team looking ahead we do have two personnel that are slated to go to the FEMA medical specialist training again that that will give us the opportunity to receive the federal training through FEMA and will be teamed on
some of the urban search and rescue task force that get called out to major emergencies throughout the country. We wanted to try to incorporate the new technology through the GSI mapping and the drone program
and hopefully working with the police department and using the drone for search and rescue throughout the city and even with some of the fires if we can get the drones up and flying and kind of circle that building we can develop a strategy of how we'll attack the emergency
through from a vertical view there so our fire suppression division again like i said that's the kind of who most people see day to day in 2000 or in 25 we did promote one new lieutenant
assigned to ladder one with his promotion that brings our our frontline apparatus fully staffed
with the firefighters and a fire officer for the first time probably since 20 or yet 2016
and so we're now we're fully back to where we should be with our officer complement and our
firefighters and that was just through attrition and through COVID a lot of promotions weren't
happening. And just as we would get promotions done, more people were retiring and we wouldn't
have the staff to move into those positions. Again, we did outfit that squad, the new suppression
engine. We're now working a lot more enhanced coordination with LEMSA. As many of you know, they have a new facility over on Fairview Avenue. So we're taking a lot of training together and really working hand in hand. So we're more familiar with each other on scenes as the emergencies happen. Penn Medicine 1 is an emergency physician, which is in a chase truck. And that unit, when not on duty, is housed at our Station 3 on East King Street. And that just brings a lot more training with it. We're able to bounce a lot of stuff off and get trains from those doctors that are on the streets and I have a really firsthand name basis with them as we as they come in and out of the buildings so some of the goals for these the suppression division working with the Water Bureau we want to try to get our hydrants flow tested so we can start marking them with the with a flow rate using the NFPA color coding system that that was one of the one of suggestions that that could have bumped us up to a better ISO rating through the insurance services and give us a better insurance rating for the city residents we continue we'll continue to secure additional training buildings and what that is we're just building partnerships and as buildings are being renovated we
get in there before the renovation starts and we're able to pretty much help them in renovation and knocking walls out cutting some of the roof apart and getting the hands-on training that you just don't get unless a building's on fire so our fire marshal's office uh they've had a really strong year in prevention and for enforcement they've added 156 new licensed businesses they are completely nearly 800 total inspections across the city they have conducted in conjunction with the health
department 31 food truck inspections 35 large tent inspections that we require permits throughout the city for community events they've also fully transitioned their electronic inspections through our records management system which we are still working through most of those modules and getting them up up and fully operational this allows the inspector and the inspectors to generate photo-rich digital reports right on scene and email it right to the business for improved
compliance. We also partnered with what's called the Compliance Engine, which is a third-party distributor or data collection. And what that does is all the companies that do your sprinkler inspections, your fire alarm inspections, anything to do with the fire safety, we put it in the code
they're they're required to upload a report to the compliance engine and what we're able to find businesses that are have hood systems or automatic suppression systems that we didn't know about and we're able to collect the collect the permits for those and get those uh facilities inspected so in 26 the goal for the uh the fire marshals division is is to get that to 100 so that every contractor is reporting uh as they're doing inspections in the city so we
can we can get that um get our permits and our licenses up to date with that uh and again that'll identify the business still missing the proper license and inspections um we're also working on strengthening of our um our certificate of fitness and that's just uh when we a business comes in and wants to do work in the city we issue a certificate of fitness and saying that they
are certified to work in the city on the fire suppression or fire alarm systems again one of the biggest things that we've really tried to develop over the last two years and really it really started moving forward in 25 is the emergency management division our emergency
management division has led several major preparedness initiatives over 25. they we've adopted the city's continuing continuity of operations plan updated the emergency communications annex adopted the new County hazard mitigation plan and the team has also conducted the CPR training for City Hall the operations center and
wastewater staff and this just helps to build a more resilient citywide workforce and 26 as you all know we'll update the the coop with the alignment the incoming administration they're in plans to develop the mass casualty annex to strengthen our
special event responses and we're hoping to conduct four city-wide emergency exercise to test our emergency operations center readiness and continuing engagement with the new city
leadership that will be coming in to refine that preparedness so our administration uh division kind of more impactful behind the scenes uh that the person that runs that division has successfully led a recruitment drive this year as you know we we held a recruitment drive every
other year to get a new civil service hiring list with helped on board the new firefighter for 25
managed a in the process of managing a new personal protective equipment wear test trial to evaluate the next generation of firefighting equipment and gear they has also advanced our community risk reduction and standards of cover development which are two major long-term initiatives for the bureau so in 26 the focus on the administrative is going to be improving in the internal processes and the integrating the digital workflows through our rms and our nearest transition and finalizing that five-year strategic plan for the bureau so as you can see our expenses a large part of our expenses
are the salaries and fringe and the pension the fringe benefits and pension we've actually we're able to reduce our other expenses through really going line by line and seen comparing through the last few years budgets of where we can reduce that uh that line item and
support the three percent raise that will be due for the staff in 26. so it's overall it's a 2.2 increase in our budget and we are proposing like i said we are proposing one uh one new staff if um
if our all our other staff stays with us uh we we do have one one staff member that has to retire
that um but that is in uh september of 26. so all the other ones will stay the same other than the suppression division we'll hopefully add that one new uh firefighter and that's some of our grant uh some of the grant the 25 uh did have a grant that we uh received we did buy uh two new uh gear
washers uh replaced gear washers that were over 30 years old to enhance the new equipment and a
little more efficient and bigger that we can wash more gear at one time and it's really the budget
for the fire bureau all right thank you chief any questions or comments from council council president thank you um chief hutchinson thank you so much and i commend you on the pretty modest
increase in the budget uh for the year a couple questions um we i know you mentioned uh the
apparatus put in service the very end tail end of 2024 um are do you anticipate any additional apparatus replacements in the next year just looking on the horizon for 26 early 27 we will have to put a committee together to replace one of our aerial apparatus following the 15-year replacement plan that was adopted through the city council that apparatus will come due in 2034 but we're anticipating probably a two-year planning process and as of right now if we would order that ladder truck it would be a four-year wait time before we'd even take
delivery of it yeah that's i know there's a long lead time for those the lead time for the apparatus that we took uh delivery for in 24 and that is your basic suppression engine that's not a specialized aerial piece and that was over two years till we took delivery of that thank you i also had a question about you mentioned the mandated upgrades to the record keeping system and the communications um just i probably know the answer to this but um those mandates they come with any additional funding support to get that done or is that unfunded and no it's uh unfunded mandates the the nearest is um we wouldn't have to follow that but then if we would not follow the nearest program and upgrade to it we would not be eligible for any grant through the federal or state okay makes sense um and then my last question is um the revenue lines do they reflect any reimbursements for like the special operations uh team time spent outside of
the city is that part of it it's kind of a cost neutral when they when they respond outside we
we get a reimbursement which goes back into our our general fund line item for any cost and usually it's overtime cost and that goes right back in and if you look at the budget you'll see that there's some deposits in that through the cert team through the county through the south central
task force and eventually once we partner with the federal uh the federal there's a little more money there that you can actually recoup the salary and the overtime got it so yeah thank you
yeah Thank You council president any other questions or comments from the public yeah this should actually be pretty pretty quick yeah in terms of comments 2.2 percent is a beautiful percentage increase particularly in one of the largest line items in yeah 14 14 million dollars 17 percent of the city budget that is that is fantastic two questions then president bake a address the equipment question upcoming equipment with regard to recruitment I know that this has been an ongoing issue is that has that improved is that looking that that has improved greatly we had over 250 applicants in this cycle for recruitment and we when we have that many we take we interviewed the top 40
and that list should be certified they have one more chance to pass the physical agility test and I believe we have a civil service meeting scheduled for November 11th to serve how that list you referenced 2,000 emergency calls how
many of those were fires I'd have to get the breakdown for that ballpark one-third one-half now it the fire responses are probably 10 percent of our responses your rescues your
false alarms your good intent your emergency medical services that plays a much larger
response in percentage in our responses and lastly on budget for 25 was 13.7 actual is projected at
13.2 is that due to not filling positions or something else uh that's due to our uh
diligence on reigning in overtime uh from the past uh few years and you expect to be able to do the same in 26. uh we're hoping to yes thank you thank you any additional questions from the public thank you thank you chief hutchinson thank you all right and our for last but definitely not
least uh for this evening uh chief mendez with the police bureau good evening all right all right the
honor of being last i promise uh not to take too much time i'm actually told i have the quickest one so we'll get right to the point with ours and hopefully get everyone out of here at a reasonable time all right first we'll start like everyone did with our organizational chart um pretty standard We have three divisions, patrol, which is the uniformed officers, CID, which is our detectives.
And I'll point out with that the change you may notice from years past is we reorganized a little bit after our staffing study and with some of our manpower issues the past year, and we now have just two main units in detectives,
which is major crimes and special investigations. so we consolidated property crimes and with our major crimes and our detectives will handle all cases at this point. Special investigations is a little different because that's a lot of our sexual assault crimes and our children crimes, so we kept that separate from our other investigators. And we moved the Selective Enforcement Unit under the command of the investigative division as well.
and then admin division again that's the support staff records division training the pie chart you've seen numerous times we'll highlight ours it's the the largest portion 37 percent of the
city budget is the police bureau we'll get into a little bit of that later with what those costs
are some bureau highlights for 2025 we've talked a lot about accreditation but it's one of our biggest accomplishments we've had. As a police bureau, we are fully accredited
agency, which obviously shows that we are doing the best standards and practices in policing. We hired our largest class of police officers in over 20 years. Um, and I'll point out like our recruitment has been amazing. It
has been a team effort across the city. I would like to take all the credit for that but it's not just me you know people want to love where they work and
you know I think the city of Lancaster is a very you know overall great place
to be employed so you know and kudos to our comms team DJ Amber Stacia and Wyatt who do a fantastic job with our recruitment and all our officers that are making phone calls to to recruits um and just as a point uh we have on our next test i believe 70 so far signed up and a neighboring county had six or seven seven show up at their last
so we are doing a tremendous uh job here and i won't point out the neighboring county
we've revamped our citizens police academy which i know some of you are uh went to last first class was last wednesday second is tomorrow so we're excited for that again it's a new revamp so looking for a lot of feedback for those of you that are attending it and hopefully you can
get something valuable out of it we're extremely proud to put that on we hosted our first national
laid out the police station we got a we were unsure how that was going to go and it actually
went extremely well we got a lot of positive feedback and our officers were still able to attend some of the the localized neighborhood events as well so we're all happy with that
our sworn staff have completed over close to 15,000 hours of training this past year so
again I'll just point out you have one of the best trained police departments around and we
take a lot of pride in that and we are implementing a new records management report management system
mark 43 that was you know out of necessity to become NIBRS compliant it's one of our expenses
we'll get into but you know we're undertaking that and that'll transition into 2026 when it's implemented 2026 goals first one up there is you'll be having a new
police chief next year at some point as I'll be retiring so you know obviously
getting that police chief in and call it up to speed is going to be something that's critical for the agency but I do feel with you know everything we've done the past few years that that person will be stepping into a great police department and Coney get better so that's a goal and then improve recruitment and marketing strategies for police officers cadet and some of our civilian positions we're constantly you know needing to fill positions we've done great with the police officer cadets have been going well as but we do still have CSA positions and some other civilian positions that constantly recruiting for the good thing with how we've done some of our recruitment is a
lot of our civilian positions with our hiring recently have been able to transition into police
officer role so it's been from cadet to police officer some civilian positions it's been a nice pipeline for us department expenses you'll see the increase in salaries plus seven percent obviously we have the cba which is always going to be a modest increase and i think the highlight there is that we you you will have a fully uh we're close to fully staffed police department
at 128 which is uh the the increase um in the past budgets we we didn't have that
and i'll also point out that we did the staffing study in 2024 to really show what what lancaster city should have in terms of a police department size and where that staff should be uh should should be at so you know we're we're seeing those fruits now so fringe benefits again up 2.6 percent other expenses 3.3 some of those other expenses that we'll touch on one I mentioned earlier mark 43 we have to be NIBRS compliant it's a FBI mandate with reporting and our current system is is not so we had to out of necessity look for a system that was and with that comes that that cost of implementing it and then also training was another increase with the highest class of you know 20 recruits there comes training
with that through the Academy some of that does then get you know refunded through MoPEC which would go back into the general fund but we pay that cost up front those are some of the high cost with other expenses and overall it's an
increase of 4.9 percent department staffing we budgeted for 114 in 2025 uh proposed for 2026 is to have a fully staffed police department at 128 increase of 14. civilian staff you can see we are eliminating minus four for the full time we increased some part-time staff in records but it's still a negative of four for our civilian staff revenue we don't generate a ton of revenue i'll just highlight that you know with the revenue uh there's been a consistent
steady decrease in parking violations revenue over the past few years so that's the decrease in that that you'll see and i know director campbell touched on the grants we don't list that because we're not really sure what 2026 is gonna get us in far as our our federal grants
and i apologize i got through all this and i realized i never let anyone know who was with me that's captain uh whiteford uh he is the man behind the budget uh he's the administrative captain so i'm sorry but welcome bob whiteford and with that uh hopefully i uh was as quick as I promise to be and open up to any questions or comments. Okay Thank You chief any questions or comments from council councillors Thank You councillor. Thank You chief Mendez For the presentation. Thank you captain my friend So my question is about the staffing levels Where are we at as far as? Hired officers currently are we at the full?
one fourteen one twenty eight would be the full staffing we would anticipate for 2026 we are at
I think 110 or 112 currently of the 114 that are hired like currently uniformed yes okay and then how many i know you said there's 70 that are doing the is that the agility test that you were referring to how many would you anticipate potentially being up for higher than so out of
this off of our last test we just took we anticipate uh swearing in january 10 to 12 new officers at the start of the year um each class we've had really good success so we've been able to get about 10 hires out of each group so um honestly a lot of that comes down to the candidates and you know whether they're passing and if there are people that you know are passing the background
to work in leicester city and then my last question around that would be um how many officer retirements do you anticipate either happening before the end of the year or in 2026 so I think 2026 is just me yeah the next big class that we do project out the next
the next time you're going to see a hit with retirements is 2028 January of 2028 it evens out a little bit right now in 2028 there's a significant I think it's close to maybe double digits that would be eligible for retirement that'll be the next largest retirement class we track all that I don't have it with me he's going to leave yeah so we have one for this in 26 and it'll probably be 27 and I also want to say congratulations to you Chief Mendez
and all the fantastic work all the things that you listed the accreditation the incredible success with recruiting you've clearly done excellent work you and your team So I just wanted to commend you and and thank you for your service to the city. All right. Thank you Councillor Craig
Thank you. I echo my colleague and Wanted to know Is there is there a limit an age limit to retirement just out of curiosity
60 is the the age we have to retire as warrant officers. Okay. Thank you council president thank you I didn't want to say anything that's an important
point of clarification I asked the question because do you look rather
young to retire I have two two questions kind of in the weeds maybe a little bit but um so you're probably thankful that this is your last budget that you need to do um there i noticed a line for on-call um captains um can you talk a little bit about what that means and it says that there's a note that says it was added to track it how have we done this before and what
exactly does that mean so it came out of a different line item before so the new line item was added so um every night after hours there's a duty captain who takes calls um and basically you know the the shift oic the lieutenant working or sergeant will handle this you know any issues that come up if there is you know a homicide or if they have a question or there's a shooting or there's something that may generate news uh they could go down a range of different reasons why they would call one of the the duty captain and it could be to get advice to advise them of something
and that's the compensation for that got it and then i also noticed an increase for community
service aids can you talk a little bit about why we anticipate needing that for the upcoming year it looks like um it looks like we increased it in 2025 but we haven't used all of that for this year So I'm just kind of curious. Yeah, that would come down to staffing. We've been understaffed for years. So got it
And for everyone's education what do community service aides what type of work do they do? So if we're fully staffed they do a ton but there they are typically at station we the cells
So if we have any prisoners, they are they you know monitor that make sure they're okay get them processed in they do fingerprinting
pick you know photos of arrestees they help with warrant checks they do toes it's a it's a lot of
job it's a lot of work but it takes it away from an officer so the officer can be out there when we're fully staffed we also have the ability to send them out and they can handle some of the
minor calls like parking issues noise complaints things of those natures okay so currently because that has been understaffed we're pulling officers off to do some of that work a lot of that work all of that work yes okay got it thank you very much thank you council president councilman uh thank you council royal and thank you both for the presentation um i had two questions first around the professional standards office are we going to be adding any additional staff i know
that with the new accreditation there's a lot of work that goes into the professional standards
is that still going to kind of be like a one-man office or are we planning to add additional resources we need an additional person there typically there was another sergeant there our
staffing just is not allowed for it ideally i would love to put someone up there now because
we are you know we we are demanding a lot from the lieutenant that's up there right now so um ideally yes we do need to fill that position thank you and with the grant awards is there a particular officer or sergeant who is doing the grant right who's doing the grant writing for the department that goes out of director campbell's office okay and then lastly you know each year when we look
at the police budget you know a question comes to my mind on you know what can we do and what can
the community do to kind of advocate for a higher state contribution towards pensions to kind of give a little bit of relief to municipalities across the state given that it's kind of a flat you know contribution from the state you know what are ways that we could kind of advocate for more money for police bureaus and for pensions from the state probably a director campbell question i'm not really sure what we what more we can do um yeah i i i can try and get you an answer to that i don't have it right now though thank you i don't want to put her on the spot but
i don't have the answer to that i mean they don't have a real good answer except to just say keep advocating i mean you can see you saw in the october 6 presentation that our our costs with that continue to increase every year exponentially compared to what we get from the state so it's important to keep advocating for more from the state yeah and with you
know upcoming retirements and you know fringe benefits you know going up year over year I just think you know it would behoove all of us to kind of try to get the state to you know give more to police bureaus and retired officers and
kind of relief relieve municipalities who are taking on the burden of that
that cost Thank You councillor men any additional questions or comments counselors so I had another question the crossing guards I noticed I think a
couple were added pay was bummed and I if I remember it but I don't know if it was a new position or not but an admin assistant can talk about kind of what the goals are around increasing that program increasing the pay and also trying to I imagine recruiting is difficult and I'm sure that's part of it but am I correct in saying that the admin assistant in that line was added and if so what would their function be so we didn't add a admin assistant yeah we had one retire who was off long term and then we're gonna we fill that position yeah as far as school crossing guards chiefs looking at me because this has been an ongoing source of consternation and I want to give credit
to a sergeant summer all who is going to work very difficult very hard to fill those positions but when the budget was originally presented to me it was that
they were going to fill all of those positions and I did not think that that was completely realistic and so not all of the crossing guard positions are
filled but they are listed there and we are having some discussion at our comms
meeting about and this was one of the goals that was highlighted earlier in chief's remarks was how can we utilize some of the recruitment and marketing strategies that
we've used for police officers for cadets csa positions and also crossing guards that i would just add to that in terms of a 2026 goal so that that's on the horizon we know how critical those positions are especially as the you'll hear from the other director campbell related to our vision
zero efforts and our safe routes to schools so we know that those positions are are very critical in the city and we appreciate all the crossing guards that we have because uh is a really really
thankless and tough job um and um and so yes i think that's all i have to say about that i don't
know if there's anything else to add yeah i would just add that it is a tough position to fill because it's a hour two in the morning an hour two in the afternoon so to get yelled at yeah an hour in the morning to yell that and then an hour or two in the afternoon there's been a ton of discussion as the mayor said there's been a ton of discussions but it's been a tough position
from what i've seen it's worse than thankless it's i've seen the abuse that some of them endure and
it's unfortunate it's a bad reflection on our drivers particularly in our community and i would just say i do really hope that i told sergeant summerall that i hope that he proves me wrong and fills every one of those positions i would love to see that as well thank you
great any additional questions or comments from council from the public while he walks over you uh amy stoltz is one of our black south arch street uh chief can you say a little bit about the park ranger roles i know that that was a recommendation in the parks master plan um the city and the police department did a bit of a pilot with invictus uh this year uh we we i
work as a soe director for temple we did a lot of coordination with invictus and i thought that was really successful um is that in in the budget for next year kind of what are what is the police department thinking about that role so we ran it through i believe we cut the hours back a little bit right now over the winter months i know it's going to be re-evaluated our hope is with our incoming recruitment classes that we will have the staffing to uh you know one fill our patrol officers that they're able to take on some of that role because it is it has been an increase that was significant with paying invictus so we do need to look at other other other things to alleviate some of that cost okay so is the the idea is to kind of evaluate that partnership with evictus and potentially hire them again next year correct well we'll re-evaluate it um next
year and is and is the park ranger kind of position sort of off the table uh at this point as a kind of a it's a you know kind of a different role within the police department yeah i don't know if we i wouldn't say it's off the table or on the table um evictus filled the role uh filled
it nicely um we'll reevaluate in january uh the police department will reevaluate in january and then go from there okay yeah i would just say from you know uh someone who does a lot of work in
the community particularly around colleton park like i thought uh the invictus partnership was great i think that that park ranger role is is critically needed so i would love for uh the
department and council to consider that in future years yeah the only thing i would add with the park rangers um when you create a position that they're now city employees it's you know is you you have that position yeah so it's it's a long-term investment yeah thank you 800 block of george street um yeah so first of all uh congratulations on your upcoming retirement um also um huge huge congratulations on achieving accreditation um that has all kinds of you know
positive benefits for the department the city and so forth so that's that's amazing that's absolutely fantastic so broadly speaking what I'm coming up to advocate for is I do think that the city budget in what essentially is a
Goldilocks economy we have very low unemployment we have 2.9 percent
inflation last year we had a 5.5 percent general fund increase we're trying to to not raise the EIT over another 10 years. The current budget is proposing a 6.5% general fund increase and a reserve drawdown of $859,000 and change. I just don't think that's the right recipe for 2026.
I think funding police adequately and having as many officers on the street
to get the job done is hugely important,
but it is also the largest line item in the budget by far. And if you want to make significant cuts, you've got to look where the money is being spent.
So with that as kind of a preface,
I wanted to ask about the staffing. It sounds like the budgeted staffing is 114 positions in 2025, 128 positions in 2026. But if I heard you correctly, we actually only currently
have 104 sworn officers and the intent is to increase that by 10 ish which would be I guess 114 so my question is how does that then relate to the
top-line budget for the police department that I'm seeing if we're at 114 instead of 128 does that mean that we'll be spending less than the number
I'm seeing here chief can I can I do that because we went back and forth on on this and you actually were not involved because it didn't change the number but it changed line items what we've done in the budget is that there
are a number of staff positions police officer positions that are funded at
half and so you can you'll see that every officer position is budgeted but ten I believe I believe it's ten right are budgeted at half so we're not fully budgeting all of the police officers for 2026 for an entire 12-month period of time the other thing that I I I'm just gonna mention to counsel is that in 2027 when all of those officers are in for a full year of salary that is also when we're hoping to see pretty significant reductions in our overtime expenses those overtime expenses are they're budgeted at 1.1 million for next year which is actually what I was gonna ask about yes and so what we because we're going to be half a year we're still not fully staffed we are keep we are including some cushion
related to those overtime expenses but we are anticipating that they will diminish however
it's very difficult for us to predict what our overtime expenses are on a year-to-year basis when we're not fully staffed so with this is going to be this has been a challenge for the Bureau and I give a lot of credit to Chief and Bob for how they have had to manage that and we've been working down because we cannot fill all of the overtime positions that are posted and I'll let you guys speak to that but this is to say that I am anticipating that in 2026 that overtime
budget will be less and then in 2027 it should be significantly less because we will be at full
staffing so it's a process to get us there um chief do you want to add anything to that yeah
the only thing i would add is we have three hiring cycles that we'll be accounting for so if we continue with our success we should be fully staffed and i think the mayor did a good job
of explaining everything else can you address the public safety impact of having a complement of
100 and i guess ultimately 128 versus 114. what what does that mean again in terms of enhanced safety quicker response to crime and so forth because i think if i mean that's the trade-off ultimately the city council has to weigh i guess another question would be how much does an individual officer cost per year in salary benefits and what city council i think has to away is the incremental effect of one additional officer on the street and the public safety enhancement that provides versus the budget that we're seeing here I can I just say I mean that's
why we did the staffing study we were at 145 officers we looked at our call volume there was a pretty extensive process that went through for the staffing study to get us to that our city needed 128 officers based on the call volume the crime rates etc etc i can't even list off all of the things that they looked at i'll look to chief but that's how we got 128 and so i think for you
to ask council to weigh in on what that number is they they should rightly point back to the staffing study that was done by a group of experts that came in to do this analysis i think it's
pretty significant that we've gone from a 145 to 128 that is an enormous amount of savings to budget over time and we're that we're not staffing at a level that's not appropriate to the call volume of our city and it speaks to the gains that we've made in safety our homicide rates are down et cetera et cetera i gotta stop talking because i jinx it but you see where i'm going tim and so i would say that that staffing study does answer your questions about what the relative need is for policing and the reduction from 145 to 128 speaks to the efforts that we've made to address what is the value and what should that number be in terms of maintaining public
safety in the city and i would just add that the staffing study didn't just tell us what the number of officers should be it told us when we should be deploying those officers the times so we looked at that and we adjusted our minimum staffing around those times which when we're fully
staffed will cut down significantly as well on cost if i could ask um the incremental cost of one officer roughly speaking uh new officers i think start out at 65 65 000 um fringe benefits
30 about 30 30 000 for fringe benefits thanks very much yeah thank you uh marshall miller 100
block of east fine street i thank you for the presentation tonight and for your service you guys have a tough job and i think you do it well um quick question just around enforcement priorities if you're up to the full 128 officers does that give you a little bit of a like a flexibility where the officers maybe have more time and ability to focus on enforcement priorities that are non-emergency when they're on shift and if so can we prioritize things like traffic related violations or small electric vehicles on sidewalks this is a danger concern that i've heard repeatedly
from folks and i'm just curious to hear your perspective on that yeah so i think the short real answer is yes it can prioritize some of those things um right now obviously our we have a duty to respond to calls for service which i think is typically 30 to 40 000 a year so yes it will increase more of that but i would also add as you know you guys are well aware i am big on community engagement so it will also give the officers more time to be out involved in their community doing
stuff more than just enforcement which will have a positive effect positive effect on the city that's great and actually bleeds into my second question which one of your two goals was to continue your engagement and recruitment improvements that you've been working on and I'm wondering how high of a priority is recruiting both civilian and officer personnel from within the city limits so it's always a
priority but it's you know recruitment is hard this police profession is hard so um at the end of the day we went the we want the best people to be police officers we focus on you know obviously we want our police department to to represent the community and you know be a part of that community but at the end of the day we'll take the best officers we can get the best employees we can get thank you i appreciate it any additional public comment great well thank you chief and congratulations on retirement at the end of this year you've done a phenomenal job in your tenure here and really appreciated your leadership thank you all right thank you congrats on your last budget ever I'll come back yeah no you well thank you and
council president that concludes the Finance Committee for this evening thank you very much just quickly before we adjourn this evening I'll make a note that we will hear from the rest of our departments at our next budget hearing
which will be the evening of November 18th so we'll reconvene next month with plenty of other meetings in between now and then so counselors we've reached the end of our agenda tonight I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn move a motion and a second all in favor aye we're adjourned